Let's jump in to talk about
the self-attention
mechanism of transformers.
If you can get the main
idea behind this video,
you'll understand the
most important core idea
behind what makes
transformer networks
work. Let's jump in.
You've seen how
attention is used with
sequential neural
networks such as RNNs.
To use attention with a
style more late CNNs,
you need to calculate
self-attention,
where you create
attention-based representations
for each of the words
in your input sentence.
Let's use our running example,
Jane, visite, l'Afrique,
en, septembre,
our goal will be for each word to
compute an attention-based
representation like this.
So we'll end up
with five of these,
since our sentence
has five words.
When we've computed them we'll
call the five
representations with
these five words A1through A5.
I know you're starting
to see a bunch
of symbols Q, K, and V,
we'll explain what
these symbols mean
in a later slide so don't
worry about them for now.
The running example
I'm going to use
is take the word l'Afrique
in this sentence.
We'll step through on
the next slide how
the transformer network's
self-attention mechanism
allows you to compute
A3 for this word,
and then you do
the same thing for
the other words in
the sentence as well.
Now you learn previously
about word embeddings.
One way to represent
l'Afrique would be to just
look up the word
embedding for l'Afrique.
But depending on the context,
are we thinking of l'Afrique
or Africa as a site of
historical interests or
as a holiday destination,
or as the world's second
largest continent.
Depending on how you're
thinking of l'Afrique,
you may choose to
represent it differently,
and that's what this
representation A(3) will do.
It will look at the
surrounding words
to try to figure out what's
actually going on in how
we're talking about
Africa in this sentence,
and find the most appropriate
representation for this.
In terms of the
actual calculation,
it won't be too different from
the attention mechanism you saw
previously as applied
in the context of RNNs,
except we'll compute
these representations
in parallel for all five
words in a sentence.
When we're building
attention on top of RNNs,
this was the equation we used.
With the self-attention
mechanism,
the attention equation is
instead going to look like this.
You can see the equations
have some similarity.
The inner term here also
involves a softmax,
just like this term
over here on the left,
and you can think of
the exponent terms as being
akin to attention values.
Exactly how these
terms are worked
out you'll see in the next slide.
So again, don't worry about
the details just yet.
But the main
difference is that for
every word, say for l'Afrique,
you have three values called
the query, key, and value.
These vectors are
the key inputs to
computing the attention
value for each words.
Now, let's step through the steps
needed to actually calculate A3.
On this slide, let's step through
the computations you need
to go from the words
l'Afrique to the self-attention
representation A3.
For reference, I've
also printed up here on
the upper-right that softmax-like
equation from the previous slide.
First, we're going to associate
each of the words with
three values called the
query key and value pairs.
If X3 is the word
embedding for l'Afrique,
the way that's Q3 is computed
is as a learned matrix,
which I'm going to
write as WQ times X3,
and similarly for the
key and value pairs,
so K3 is WK times
X3 and V3 is WV times X3.
These matrices, WQ, WK, and WV,
are parameters of this
learning algorithm,
and they allow you to
pull off these query,
key, and value vectors
for each word.
So what are these query key
and value vectors supposed to do?
They were named using a loose
analogy to a concept in
databases where you can have
queries and also key-value pairs.
If you're familiar with
those types of databases,
the analogy may
make sense to you,
but if you're not familiar with
that database concept,
don't worry about it.
Let me give one intuition
behind the intent of these query,
key, and value of vectors.
Q3 is a question that you
get to ask about l'Afrique.
Q3 may represent a question
like, what's happening there?
Africa, l'Afrique
is a destination.
You might want to know when
computing A^3, what's
happening there.
What we're going to do is compute
the inner product
between q^3 and k^1,
between Query 3 and Key 1,
and this will tell us
how good is an answer
where it's one to
the question of what's
happening in Africa.
Then we compute the
inner product between
q^3 and k^2 and this
is intended to tell
us how good is visite an
answer to the question of
what's happening in Africa and so
on for the other words
in the sequence.
The goal of this operation is to
pull up the most
information that's needed
to help us compute
the most useful
representation A^3 up here.
Again, just for
intuition building
if k^1 represents that
this word is a person,
because Jane is a person,
and k^2 represents
that the second word,
visite, is an action,
then you may find that
q^3 inter producted
with k^2 has the largest value,
and this may be
intuitive example,
might suggest that visite,
gives you the most
relevant contexts
for what's happening in Africa.
Which is that, it's viewed as
a destination for a visit.
What we will do is take
these five values in
this row and compute
a Softmax over them.
There's actually this
Softmax over here,
and in the example that
we've been talking about,
q^3 times k^2 corresponding
to word visite maybe
has the largest value.
I'm going to shade
that blue over here.
Then finally, we're going to take
these Softmax values and
multiply them with v^1,
which is the value for word 1,
the value for word 2, and so on,
and so these values correspond
to that value up there.
Finally, we sum it all up.
This summation corresponds to
this summation operator
and so adding up
all of these values
gives you A^3,
which is just equal
to this value here.
Another way to write
A^3 is really as A,
this A up here of q^3,
k, v. But sometimes it will be
more convenient to just
write A^3 like that.
The key advantage of
this representation is
the word of l'Afrique isn't
some fixed word embedding.
Instead, it lets the
self-attention mechanism
realize that l'Afrique is
the destination of a visite,
of a visit, and thus
compute a richer,
more useful representation
for this word.
Now, I've been using
the third word,
l'Afrique as a running example
but you could use this
process for all five
words in your sequence to get
similarly rich
representations for Jane,
visite, l'Afrique, en, septembre.
If you put all of these
five computations together,
denotation used in
literature looks like this,
where you can summarize all
of these computations
that we just talked
about for all the words in
the sequence by
writing Attention(Q,
K, V) where Q, K,
V matrices with all
of these values,
and this is just
a compressed or
vectorized representation
of this equation up here.
The term in the denominator
is just to scale the dot-product,
so it doesn't explode.
You don't really need
to worry about it.
But another name for
this type of attention
is the scaled
dot-product attention.
This is the one represented in
the original transformer
architecture paper,
Attention Is All
You Need As Well.
That's the
self-attention mechanism
of the transformer network.
To recap, associated with each of
the five words you
end up with a query,
a key, and a value.
The query lets you ask a
question about that word,
such as what's
happening in Africa.
The key looks at all
of the other words,
and by the similarity
to the query,
helps you figure out
which words gives
the most relevant answer
to that question.
In this case, visite is what's
happening in Africa,
someone's visiting Africa.
Then finally, the value
allows the representation to
plug in how visite should
be represented within A^3,
within the representation
of Africa.
This allows you to come up with
a representation for the word
Africa that says this is
Africa and someone
is visiting Africa.
This is a much more nuanced,
much richer representation
for the world than if you
just had to pull up the
same fixed word embedding
for every single word
without being able
to adapt it based
on what words are to
the left and to the
right of that word.
We've all got to take into
account and in the context.
Now, you have learned about
the self-attention mechanism.
We're going to put
a big for-loop
over this whole thing and that
will be the multi-headed
attention mechanism.
Let's dive into the details
of that in the next video.